Jane White Papers, 1924-2001 (ongoing)
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Jane White Papers
1924-2001 (ongoing)
White, Jane
MS 262
5 boxes (3.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Actress. Papers include scripts, newspaper clippings, notes, publicity, correspondence, audiotapes, interviews, scrapbooks, and photographs. These materials, enhanced by White's eloquent self-reflections in interviews generated by her work on stage, document the career of a versatile performer. While the collection primarily documents White's professional career and the challenges she faced as an African American actress, her husband Alfredo Viazzi and her prominent parents, Walter and Gladys White, are also represented.
Biographical Note
Jane White was born on October 30, 1922 to Walter and Leah Gladys (Powell) White. The Whites stood among the elites of the Harlem Renaissance. Walter White, a native of Atlanta, Georgia, rose through the ranks of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) to become national secretary of the organization in 1931. He published several acclaimed works, including Rope and Faggot (1929), an analysis of lynching funded by a Guggenheim fellowship, the novels The Fire in the Flint (1924) and Flight (1926), and his autobiography A Man Called White (1948). By many accounts an exceptionally beautiful woman, Gladys White had been employed as a stenographer at the New York office of the NAACP and had a rich musical heritage from her father, a Jubilee singer, which she put to good use as a performer in a Broadway musical Deep River (1926). Known as the "White House of Harlem," their apartment in the fashionable Sugar Hill neighborhood served as the setting for a range of cultural and social evenings. As children, Jane and her brother Walter Carl Darrow, born in 1927, absorbed the artistic and intellectual influence of their parents as well as such regular guests as James Weldon Johnson, Paul and Eslanda Robeson, Carl Van Vechten, and George Gershwin. Jane's career as an actress and her brother's work as an opera singer and television writer indicate the lasting impact of this creative milieu.
Jane White's education reflected Walter White's political philosophy. Looking to integrate elite educational institutions, which often remained exclusively white in the socially separate 1920s, 30s, and 40s, he negotiated admission of his daughter to the Ethical Culture Schools of New York City and later, with the cooperation of Smith President Emeritus William Allan Neilson, to Smith College. In college, Jane majored in Sociology in order to follow in the path of her father's social activism, but she maintained a stronger passion for the arts. She minored in music, studying classical voice with Anna Hamlin, and participated in extracurricular dance and fencing. In 1943 she also served as the president of the student House of Representatives, making her the first African American elected to serve in a government position at Smith.
She was graduated in 1944 and worked for a short time as a proofreader for the Research Institute of America while she also attended beginners' acting classes at New York's New School. In 1945 she secured her first stage role, the lead in a high profile Broadway production. José Ferrer was staging Lillian Smith's Strange Fruit, a controversial novel about interracial love in the South, and sought an actress for the role of Nonnie, a light-complexioned, small-town black woman whose white lover ultimately spurns her. Paul Robeson, a friend of the White family, suggested Jane for the part, and her inexperience did not hamper a successful audition. Though critical response to the play was mixed, it did well, particularly after Eleanor Roosevelt praised it-and White's performance-in her column, "My Day." In the fifteen years following this debut, White pursued the time-honored learning arc of an acting career with stints in summer stock, on Broadway and off, and acting instruction under various teachers, including Uta Hagen. Her broad recognition in the theatre world ultimately came with the highly successful off- Broadway to Broadway run of Once Upon A Mattress, the musical comedy that served as a launching vehicle for Carol Burnett. A role as the domineering queen showcased White's commanding stage presence and ushered in a spate of portrayals of similarly powerful women in Shakespearean and classical pieces throughout the 1960s and into the 1990s. She won the 1965-66 Obie award for her performances in the New York Shakespeare Festival as the Princess of France in Love's Labor's Lost and Volumnia in Coriolanus, and the 1988-89 Los Angeles Critics Circle Award for the Mother in Lorca's Blood Wedding.
Despite these critical successes, White grew dissatisfied with the range of roles offered to her, a problem particularly complicated by her skin tone, which made her "too black for white roles-and this really hurt-too white for black roles." Her light complexion, shared with her father who had used it to his advantage by crossing the color line to investigate crimes against blacks in the South, often worked against her in the literal-minded American theatre, compelling her to use make-up to create a distinctly Anglo-Saxon look for the stage. Even so, White found that she was often not considered for roles because she did not fit the cliché image of a black woman. Frustrated, she and her husband Alfredo Viazzi, an Italian-born restaurateur and writer whom she had wed in 1962, relocated to Rome in 1965. In Europe, her roles ironically included a critically acclaimed stage performance in Trumpets of the Lord, a piece about the black church based on the writings of Walter White's mentor, James Weldon Johnson. In the late 1960s, the Viazzis returned to the U.S. In addition to work in the theatre, Jane White (who continued to use her maiden name in her profession) began a series of cabaret performances in her husband's restaurants. The genre highlighted White's versatility and led to her one-woman show, Jane White, Who?... (1979-80), which was interspersed with songs and autobiographical reminiscence. In the 1980s, the Kool Jazz Festival featured her as a soloist, and Bobby Short presented her at Town Hall for a cabaret evening.
In her personal life, White experienced the loss of many of those dear to her. Her father ended his career with the NAACP in a scandal brought on by his divorce of Gladys and remarriage to white food expert Poppy Cannon in 1948, and he died of a sudden heart attack in 1955. Her mother died in Germany in 1979 at age 85. Her brother was killed in a mountain climbing accident in 1975 at the age of 48, and her beloved husband Alfredo Viazzi succumbed to a heart attack in 1987 when he was 66.
These tragedies, however, did not slow her career. From the 1970s to the 2000s, she filled roles of imposing, strong-willed women in a gamut of productions: comedies and musicals including A Little Night Music and Follies, and such classical and dramatic works as Ghosts, Pygmalion, and Brecht's Caucasian Chalk Circle. The Metropolitan Opera presented her, in the 1983-84 and 1993-94 seasons, in spoken roles in Les Troyens and La Fille du Regiment. She also worked in television, memorably as a villain on the soap opera Search for Tomorrow, and in film, playing the role of a Park Avenue Madam in Klute and the Schoolteacher in Beloved.
Critical response to Jane White's career since her Strange Fruit debut has ranged from pans to raves but has enabled a long and varied life's work. She has been honored by the NAACP for that work. She has counted among her fans such notables as Bobby Short, playwright Moss Hart, maestro James Levine, and theatre impresario/actor Jean-Louis Barrault, as well as the numerous performers and directors with whom she has worked. Jane White died in 2011.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Jane White Papers consist of 3.75 linear ft. dating from to 1924 to 2001. Types of materials include scripts, newspaper clippings, notes, publicity, correspondence, audiotapes, and photographs.
The bulk of the papers concern Jane White's theatrical career. These materials, enhanced by White's eloquent self-reflections in interviews generated by her work on stage, document the career of a versatile performer. Her tenuous place on the color line brings into relief the shifting perceptions of racial identity over the span of the civil rights era and beyond, particularly as they emerged and developed in the professional theatre. Documents in the collection reveal White's thoughts about her personal life and political activist heritage as well as the craft of her work. There is evidence of how she constructed her characters and executed performances. A small amount of biographical information highlights White's life outside the theatre, and the many photographs show her onstage as well as in more candid poses. While the collection documents Jane White's life and work and, to a lesser extent, that of her husband Alfredo Viazzi, her perspective on her prominent family lends insight into studies of parents Walter and Gladys White.
Note: This collection has not been fully processed and additions are expected.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into three series:
I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL
II. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
III. PHOTOGRAPHS
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this finding aid.
History of the Collection
Jane White donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1989 and continued to send additions until her death in 2011.
Search Terms
Actresses--United States--Biography--Sources; African American actresses--Biography--Sources; Theater--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women in the theater--United States--History--Sources; White, Jane; White, Walter Francis, 1893-1955
Additional Information
Related Material
Associated material located in the Smith College Archives.
See also Revealing Women's Life Stories: Papers from the 50th Anniversary Celebration of the Sophia Smith Collection for an autobiographical essay by Jane White.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS (1962-2000), .5 linear ft.
  This series contains written overviews of White's life, including materials from the 1992 autobiographical performance she staged at the Sophia Smith Collection's fiftieth anniversary celebration, as well as writings and correspondence. Correspondents include Jean-Louis Barrault, Jerome Robbins, and Henry Denker. A 1958 speech on racial justice delivered to Actors' Equity and various projects undertaken by Alfredo Viazzi can be found here.
- SERIES II. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES (1948-2001), 1.7 linear ft.
  This series covers the span of White's work in theatre and onscreen, and the period from the 1960s to the 1980s is documented most extensively. Scripts, music, programs, publicity, and clippings and other printed material can be found as well as correspondence, including many congratulatory telegrams. The series also includes White's handwritten notes and reel-to-reel audiotapes from her cabaret performances. Photographs from performances are located in SERIES III. PHOTOGRAPHS, and a scrapbook that contains correspondence, clippings, and photographs documenting her work in the 1940s and 1950s is located among the oversize materials.
- SERIES III. PHOTOGRAPHS (1924-2001), 1 linear ft.
  This series contains staged and candid photos from performances, publicity shots of Jane White, and snapshots of Jane White alone, in groups, and with family and friends.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS (1962-2000)
  - Biographical writings and stage credits, circa 1993, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Actors' Equity speech: correspondence and clipping, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Life as an Actress: A Mystery Story": script, photograph photocopies, program, and publicity from White's performance at Sophia Smith Collection's "Revealing Life Stories" fiftieth anniversary symposium, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Oral history transcripts and publicity, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Fredi Washington memorial service: typescript and program, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (includes Jean-Louis Barrault), 1967-70, 1989-95, [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS--scrapbook] (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings: general, 1962-2000, n.d., [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Awards, 1965-79 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Alfredo Viazzi projects: includes correspondence, clippings, and screenplay synopsis, 1967-75, n.d., [see also SERIES II. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES -White and the Black and cabaret performances] (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Mean Anthony": story by Jane White and correspondence, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- SERIES II. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES (1948-2001)
  - Ah, Men: script, program, and clippings, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Amen: script, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Blood Wedding: programs, publicity, award, notes, script, and clippings, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 13-16)
  - Brittanicus: program, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Burnt Flowerbed: program and clippings, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Butcher's Daughter: correspondence, program, clippings, script, and notes, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 19-21)
  - Cabaret performances: programs, publicity, clippings, and reel-to-reel audiotape, 1976-77, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - [please use cassette copy of audiotape]
  - Caucasian Chalk Circle: correspondence, program, clippings, script, and music, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 24-26)
  - Cleopatra: research material, 1948-63 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Coriolanus: correspondence, clippings, programs, program notes, research material, and script, 1991, [see also New York Shakespeare Festival] (Box 1, Folder 28-30)
  - Cuban Thing: program and clippings, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - La Fille du Regiment, [see Les Troyens]
  - Follies
    - Correspondence (includes Judith Ivey), programs, and clippings(includes program to Stephen Sondheim celebration), 2001 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Script, notes, and research material (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Ghosts: program and clippings, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - God's Trombones (tribute to James Weldon Johnson): program, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Greeks: notes, programs, script, and clippings, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Heartbreak House: script, notes, and research material, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 37-39)
  - Hop, Signor!: correspondence, program, and clippings, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - I Hate Hamlet: correspondence, program, clippings, script, and notes, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 41-43)
  - Iphigenia in Aulis: correspondence, programs, and clippings, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Jane Eyre: correspondence, programs, and clippings, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Jane White, Who?...
    - Correspondence
      - San Francisco management, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - New York lawyers, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Opening night telegrams, congratulations, fan mail, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Programs, publicity, and award, 1980, [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS] (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Clippings, 1979-80 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
    - Scripts, song lyrics, corrections, 1979, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Reel-to-reel audiotapes, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - [please use cassette copies]
  - King Lear: clippings, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Kool Jazz Festival: programs, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Life and Death of King John: program, script, notes, and research material, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Liliom: includes correspondence from Jane White to Gladys White, program, clippings, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Little Night Music: clippings, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Lola: script, music, notes, and research material, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
  - Love's Labor's Lost, [see New York Shakespeare Festival (1965)]
  - Madwoman of Chaillot: contract and publicity, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Master of Thornfield, [see Jane Eyre] (Box 2)
  - Nefertiti: clippings, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - New York Shakespeare Festival (1965): correspondence, programs, and clippings from Troilus and Cressida, Love's Labor's Lost, and Coriolanus, 1965-66 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Oh Dad, Poor Dad, Mamma's Hung You in the Closet and I'm Feeling So Sad: correspondence, programs, and clippings, 1966, [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS] (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Once upon a Mattress: correspondence, programs, and clippings, 1959-64, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 23-24)
  - Petrified Prince, 1994-95
    - Correspondence (includes Harold Prince), program, and clippings, 1994-95 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Script, notes, and music, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - Pleasure of Honesty, correspondence, programs, and research material, 1993-1995 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Power and the Glory: correspondence (includes Carl Van Vechten), programs, and clippings, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Put Your Hands Together: correspondence, photograph, and program, 1982-83 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Pygmalion: program, correspondence, clippings, and script, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 31-32)
  - Razzle Dazzle: clippings, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Rosmersholm: programs, clippings, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Search for Tomorrow: clippings, 1969, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Strange Fruit: clipping, n.d., [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS--scrapbook and script] (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Take a Giant Step: program, 1953, [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS--scrapbook] (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Taming of the Shrew: correspondence, programs, and clippings, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Tennessee Williams: A Celebration: program, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Tributes to Bobby Short, 1992-93: correspondence, programs, and clippings, 1992-93 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Trojan Women: correspondence, programs, and clippings, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Troilus and Cressida, [see New York Shakespeare Festival (1965)]
  - Tropical Breeze Hotel: correspondence, clippings, notes, and research material, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Les Troyens and La Fille du Regiment: correspondence, programs, clippings, schedules, script, and music, 1983-84, 1993-94 (Box 2, Folder 43-44)
  - Trumpets of the Lord: correspondence, script, program, and clippings, 1967-68 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - White and the Black: programs and clippings, 1967-68 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - You Never Know: programs, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous performances, 1952-98 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- SERIES III. PHOTOGRAPHS (1924-2001)
  - Jane White alone, with family, and Alfredo Viazzi, 1924-circa 1970s, [see also OVERSIZE MATERIALS] (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Jane White in groups, includes Tennessee Williams, Carrie Nye, and Gael Greene, 1979-93 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Publicity shots, circa 1940s-90s (Box 3, Folder 6-9)
  - Amen, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Blood Wedding, 1988-89 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Burnt Flowerbed, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Butcher's Daughter, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Cabarets, concerts and clubs, 1975-79, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 14-16)
  - Come What May, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 16a)
  - Coriolanus, 1965, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
  - Caucasian Chalk Circle, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Cymbeline, circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 19a)
  - Follies, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Ghosts, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Greeks, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Heartbreak House, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Hop, Signor!, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - I Hate Hamlet, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Iphigenia in Aulis, 1968-69 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - It's Only a Play, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Jane Eyre, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Jane White, Who?..., 1979-80 (Box 3, Folder 29-30)
  - King Lear, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Liliom, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Little Night Music, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Lola, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Love's Labor's Lost, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Lysistrata, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Madwoman of Chaillot, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Man of Destiny, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Oh Dad, Poor Dad, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Once Upon a Mattress: photographs and album, 1961-61, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 40-41)
  - Petrified Prince, 1994-95 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Pygmalion, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Rosmersholm, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 43a)
  - Search for Tomorrow, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Strange Fruit, [see OVERSIZE MATERIALS-photograph and scrapbook]
  - Taming of the Shrew, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Trojan Women, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Tropical Breeze Hotel, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Les Troyens and la Fille du Regiment, 1983-84 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Les Troyens, 1993-94 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Trumpets of the Lord, 1967, 1969-70 (Box 3, Folder 50)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Scrapbook, 1945-57 (Box 4)
  - Biographical materials: clippings, 1978, 1999-2000, n.d.; Obie award, 1965-66 (Box 5)
  - Professional activities
    - Strange Fruit script, 1945; clippings, 1991; and publicity, 1982-2001 (Box 5)
    - Jane White, Who?...: publicity and posters, 1979-80 (Box 5)
  - Photographs and artwork: Photographs (includes White family, 1939), 1939-82; and charcoal drawing of Jane White, 1967 (Box 5)
  - Oh Dad, Poor Dad: poster, 1966 (Map-case Flat File)